*music*
We'll be right back.
All right, I'm going to, can I stand on this?
Here's what we're going to do.
You have to listen very carefully because we got, we got pellet guns to hit kids.
I'm just kidding.
We don't have any pellet guns.
Is everybody in?
Yes!
We're going to wait.
When I count to three, you're going to go up through the balloons and search for eggs.
Yes.
Be nice.
On your mark.
Wait.
One, two, three.
Oh my gosh, that's amazing.
- Good morning, man, that was an epic event.
So kudos to all of you who've been here today.
Oh my gosh, that's amazing.
Good morning, man, that was an epic event.
So kudos to all of you who made that a success.
Well, good morning.
My name is Jill Keister and I'm glad to see all of you here today.
I have a few announcements for you this morning.
Actually more than a few, but that's okay.
We're gonna roll through these.
So if you have noticed,
we have a brand new Cultivate section for our students.
We would love it if all of our students would join
and sit in that area and those black seats back there
and worship together.
As a group, we just really think that's a cool way
for them to connect and worship together.
And so we've kind of saved that spot for them.
Another announcement for our Cultivate youth group
is they're gonna go on a summer camp.
Woo, right?
Like how many of you loved summer camp, right?
So this summer camp is gonna be in July,
the 7th through the 11th.
It's gonna be at Messiah College, right?
Yeah, summer, Messiah University, not college.
Sorry, I'm old.
Okay, so Messiah University, anyone who is a rising
seventh grader through a current senior,
so even graduates of this year are eligible to attend.
But here's the thing.
We need to know if you're interested in going.
So those of you in that age group, talk to your parents.
Parents, if you have kids of that age, check it out.
See if you would be interested, if that timeframe fits.
And we need a pre-registration.
We need to make sure that we've got enough before we actually launch into a full registration for that.
So if you have any questions, you can always see Donovan or any of our youth staff about that.
So just be sure to get that pre-registration in by the 18th of May.
Our annual church spring cleanup is Saturday, May 17th.
This is just an awesome way for you guys to come out, have some fellowship, and for us to be good stewards of the property that we have.
We'll be cleaning and organizing inside, as well as taking care of our facility outside as well.
So from 8:00 to noon, come on out and join us in that cleanup.
May 30th, AM from 5:30 to 7:30, we are going to have an end of school year bash, right?
How fun is that?
There's going to be bouncy houses.
There's going to be water slides, tasty treats, and so much more.
And the best part is that there's no registration required.
So everybody is welcome, bring friends, come on out, and have a good time.
Awesome.
All right, so now, can you believe it?
We're already starting to talk about June.
It will be here before you know it.
June 1st, we are going to have a baptism Sunday.
And for those of you who have been around Canvas for a while, you understand what this Sunday is about.
It's one of the most incredible Sunday mornings.
We have the baptism pool come up.
The kids come in and get to watch that.
And if you are interested in being baptized, we would love for you to email the church office.
That's office@canvascommunity.church, and let us know.
We would love to stand with you in that public declaration of your faith.
And then, in June 21st, we are going to have an incredible conference here.
It's called Epic of Eden.
And you do not want to miss this.
From what I understand, it's a little bit of the Old Testament and how that connects to Jesus and how all of that aligns.
So the Epic of Eden, put that on your calendars, the 21st, and if you haven't noticed, our church app that we have been using is gone.
Sad.
But the good news is that we have another one, and so you need to make sure that you've downloaded this app.
You can also give through that app, and our option to text your tithe is no longer an option, but you can do it through the app.
You can still put tithe and offerings donations in the tower in the back as well.
And I think I've gotten everything.
However, we are going to be having communion this morning, so if you didn't get your little miracle cup, be sure to do that sometime between worship and the end of the message this morning.
We would love for you to participate in that with us.
And now we are going to go ahead and transition to our time of musical worship.
Canvas, go ahead and stand up.
This is my prayer in the desert
When all that's within me will shine
This is my prayer in my hunger
My God is the God who provides
And this is my prayer in the fire
In weakness or trial or pain
There is a faith proved of full worth and glory
So refine me, Lord, through the flame
And I will bring praise
I will bring praise
The weapon formed against me
The weapon formed against me shall remain
I will rejoice
I will declare
God is my victory
And this is my prayer in my prayer
This is my prayer in the battle
When triumph is still on its way
I am a conqueror and grow heir with Christ
So firm on his promise I'll stand
I will bring praise
No weapon formed against me shall remain
I will rejoice
I will bring praise
God is my victory
All of my life
In every season
You are still God
I have a reason to sing
I have a reason to worship
All of my life
In every season
You are still God
I have a reason to sing
I have a reason to worship
All of my life
In every season
You are still God
I have a reason to sing
I have a reason to worship
I will bring praise
I have a reason to sing
I have a reason to worship
I will bring praise
No weapon formed against me shall remain
I will rejoice
I will declare
God is my victory
He is here
I will bring praise
No weapon formed against me shall remain
I will rejoice
I will declare
God is my victory
He is here
This is my prayer
When favor in the harvest
When favor and providence bloom
I know I'm filled
To be emptied again
This seed I've received
I will sow
Our Scripture reading today
comes from Ezekiel 17
22-24
This is what the Sovereign Lord says
I will take a branch
from the top of the tall cedar
and I will plant it
on the top of Israel's highest mountain
It will become a majestic cedar
sending forth its branches
and producing seed
Birds of every sort
will nest in it
finding shelter
in the shade of its branches
And all the trees
will know that
it is I, the Lord
who cuts the tall tree down
and makes the short tree tall
It is I
who makes the green tree wither
and gives the dead tree new life
I, the Lord, have spoken
And I will do what I say
Amen
For mine
Naught to the cross
You crucified
All my sin and shame
It was washed
by your mercy
You are the treasure
I'll find
My reason for living
So let my life
Become an offering
To the one who is worthy
Come on church
All praise to the Lord
Most high
All praise to the one
who saved my life
All praise to Jesus Christ
High King of heaven
High King forever
He's a cool storm
The gates of my heart
The veil in between
Was torn apart
Now you hold the keys
To the grave
Amen
Cause you bring things to life
And you roll stones away
Oh praise to the Lord
Most high
All praise to the one
Who saved my life
All praise to Jesus Christ
High King of heaven
High King forever
All praise to the Lord
Most high
All praise to the one
Who saved my life
All praise to Jesus Christ
High King of heaven
High King forever
So I lift my hands up
Lay my whole life down
My whole life down
Before you
I lift my hands up
Lay my whole life down
My whole life down
It's for you
So I lift my hands up
Lay my whole life down
My whole life down
It's for you
Everyone
I lift my hands up
Lay my whole life down
My whole life down
Before you
I lift my hands up
Lay my whole life down
My whole life down
It's for you
All praise
To the Lord
Most high
All praise
To the one
Who saved my life
All praise
To Jesus Christ
High King of heaven
High King forever
All praise
To the Lord
Most high
All praise
To the one
Who saved my life
All praise
To Jesus Christ
High King of heaven
High King forever
I lift my hands up
Lay my whole life down
My whole life down
Before you
So I lift my hands up
Lay my whole life down
My whole life down
It's for you
Yeah
All praise
To the Lord
Most high
All praise
To the one
Who saved my life
All praise
To Jesus Christ
High King of heaven
High King forever
One more time
All praise
To the Lord
To the one
Who saved my life
All praise
To Jesus Christ
High King of heaven
High King forever
All my words
For sure
I've got nothing new
How could I
Expense
All my gratitude
I could sing
These songs
As I often do
Every song
Every song must end
And you never do
So I throw up my hands
Praise you again and again
Cause all that I have
Is a hallelujah
Hallelujah
And I'm blessed not much
I'm nothing else fit for me
Except for a heart singing
Hallelujah
I've got one response
I've got just one new
With my arms
With my arms stretched wide
I will worship you
So I throw up my hands
And praise you again and again
Cause all that I have
Is a hallelujah
Hallelujah
I know it's not much
I have nothing else
Fit for a king
Except for a heart singing
Hallelujah
So come on my soul
Oh don't you get shy
Oh don't you lift up your song
Cause you've got a line
Inside of those lungs
Get up and praise the Lord
Come on
Come on my soul
Oh don't you get shy on me
Lift up your song
Cause you've got a line
Inside of those lungs
Get up and praise the Lord
Come on James
Come on my soul
Oh don't you get shy on me
Lift up your song
Cause you've got a line
Inside of those lungs
Get up and praise the Lord
And praise the Lord
So I throw up my hands
And praise you again and again
Cause all that I have is a hallelujah
Hallelujah
And I know it's not much
But I've nothing else fit for a king
Except for a heart singing
Hallelujah
God we welcome you in this place this morning
We give you all the glory
All the honor
All the praise God
You are worthy of it all
And we have so much to be grateful for God
I pray that whatever season of life we're in
Whether it be joy or sadness
Pain, sickness, new beginnings God
I pray that we never forget
To fall to our knees
And give you all that we have
We can come to you with anything God
There's nothing you can't conquer
There's no battle too big
No giant too tall God
And I especially pray for the times that are good God
I pray that we find ourselves so deeply rooted in you
That no matter what storm comes
We will never fall
Because we are strong in you
God I pray for the message today
I pray that you bless it
I pray that you give us ears to hear it
And that it brings new life to us
Every day
We love you
And we thank you for your presence
In Jesus name
Amen
Hey!
Good morning, church, we haven't had the opportunity to meet yet.
My name is Corey Smith, and I have the privilege of being part of the teaching team here at
Canvas Community.
And I'm not a huge--this might offend some people in the room.
I'm planning to offend, like, everybody today, so wear your shoes.
But this may offend some people in the room.
I'm not a huge Star Wars fan, but Chris Reinhardt threatened me.
May the fourth be with you.
You're welcome.
Happy Apple Blossom Sunday.
Thank you for joining us this week.
There you go, Chris.
You're welcome.
I didn't have, like, the good slides and everything.
But if you were here with us last week, you'll remember that Kent started--kicked off our parable
series with the parables of Jesus and an overview of how parables work, and we kind of did a
dive into the parable of the sower.
If you weren't here, let me just say I'm glad you are this week, right?
And go check that out.
That way you can keep up with us as we kind of venture along this sermon series.
The goal being one, right, to familiarize ourselves with the parables, but not just our intellect,
intellect, intellect, intellect, intellect, and knowledge, but more importantly, to let them
respond appropriately to them.
Last week we learned that parables are specific stories, or specific stories with a specific intent,
that their primary purpose is to elicit a response.
I think parables deal with difficult parts of our worldview.
They're used to move past our usual defenses and get that information just around those, and that's how I am.
I want to camp out here for just a second, because I think this is super important, and I think it's easily overlooked when it comes to parables.
I have the privilege, I don't know how much of you guys know this, but I have the privilege of having one foot in the ministry and one foot in a regular run-of-the-mill job.
And I work a full-time job, and what that looks like is, I work a full-time job, sometimes Ryan lets me volunteer so he can boss me around, that's what that looks like, I'm kidding, he's fabulous.
But seriously, I think we all have experience navigating workplace relationships, meetings, and trying to get things accomplished.
And I found in my work experience that some personalities just have to have it be their idea to agree with it.
Am I alone in that?
No.
I didn't think I was, but I wanted to make sure.
And during my study, I found this phrase, and I am super guilty of it, so I need to confess something to you.
Sarcasm is a lazy man's parable.
I am proficient at lazy man's parables.
But if sarcasm is working as a lazy man's parable, it means it's trying to accomplish something.
It's trying, when I use it, I'm trying to either get you to see the fallacy of what you are thinking,
or my perceived fallacy, and you need to talk me out of it with sarcasm.
That's how I communicate back and forth.
But it means to accomplish something.
It means to perceive someone's way of thinking.
No one's mind, heart, or worldview has been changed by saying, that's dumb, we're not going to do it that way.
I mean, people try that on Facebook, right?
And it seems to be working really well.
There it is.
Lazy man's parable, right?
So why am I bringing up sarcasm?
Because I think even in a twisted way, it shows how indirect communication can be shifting in the way people think.
Let's get back to our original thought, right?
That parables deal with the difficult parts of our worldview.
They're used to move the important information past our usual defenses.
I think you and I can argue on two molehills all day, neither side conceding any ground.
But a parable, it tends to step off the molehill and present a new paradigm,
one that navigates past our defenses and expectations,
and presents itself as a buried treasure of sorts that we never realized was there.
And when I say that, it seems to be working really well on Facebook.
You all know that I am being sarcastic because you've seen it not work so well.
And the truth is, Jesus, in much of the same way,
is using parables through his word, disrupt and reframe our assumptions today.
Every time we think we've got the kingdom figured out,
a parable pulls the rug out and shows us something better.
This week, we'll be working through the parable of the mustard seed and leaven.
It's four verses, huge implications, I think.
But so, if you've got reservations for Chili's, like, real soon,
I'd probably cancel them.
I had a lot to say about four verses, so buckle up.
So, again, this is a small verse section, but don't let that turn you away.
It takes a mighty punch, and it leads us into the theme of the message,
which is this, that the kingdom of heaven begins in hidden, humble ways,
but grows with an unstoppable, transformative power.
So, remember, the people of Jesus' day were expecting a Messiah
who would ride in with armies, overthrow Rome,
and set up a kingdom that everyone could see immediately.
But Jesus describes something far more mysterious.
A revolution of the heart that would spread from person to person,
slowly but surely, and before you know it, everything would be overrun.
Jesus tells these parables immediately after the parable of the sower,
another parable about hiddenness, growth, and soil.
Together, I think they form a portrait of the nature of God's kingdom.
It's organic.
It's mysterious.
And, folks, it's always full of potential.
So, while the parable of the sower emphasizes the varying reception of the word,
these two tiny parables, the mustard seed and the leaven that we're going to talk about today,
zoom in on the way the kingdom itself functions once it's sown.
You've heard me say this, and I'm going to keep on saying it
until the Holy Spirit reveals something to me and I've got to repent of it.
But true to the word of God, the kingdom of heaven does not arrive like a conquering empire or political revolution.
It begins in somewhat obscurity.
It works in quietness, obedience, faithfulness.
And yet, it grows and spreads to eventually transform everything by the power of the Spirit.
So, with that, let's pray before getting into the word today.
Dear Heavenly Father, we thank you for this day.
We thank you for your presence here in this space.
Lord, we ask that you use your living word to penetrate our hearts today,
that my words and my intentions be hijacked by your Spirit so that people only hear from you.
We acknowledge our privilege before you, Lord, as we gather together to study together, to read together.
May our privilege not neglect the transformation that our hearts and flesh so deeply require.
We ask you do what only you can do, Lord.
Convict us of the things that we do outside, that are outside of the plans for your kingdom,
and encourage us to follow in the ways set forth by Jesus.
We pray all of this for your glory and our neighbor's good.
Amen.
Today, if you want to follow along in your Bibles, we'll be reading Matthew 13, 31 through 35.
I'll be reading out of the CSB or the Christian Standard if you want to follow along,
but we've got it up on the screen too.
So, without further ado.
He presented, he, Jesus, presented another parable to them.
The kingdom of heaven is like a mustard seed that a man took and sowed in his field.
It's the smallest of all seeds, but when it's grown, it's taller than the garden plants and becomes a tree,
so that the birds of the sky will come and nest in its branches.
He told them another parable.
The kingdom of heaven is like leaven that a woman took and mixed into 50 pounds of flour until all of it was leaven.
Jesus told the crowds these things in parables, and he did not tell them anything without a parable,
so that what was spoken through the prophet might be fulfilled.
I will open my mouth in parables, and I will declare things kept secret from the foundation of the world.
This is the word of the Lord.
Now, before we jump into the exposition of the text,
Jesus taught in parables to invite his listeners to go deeper, beyond the surface,
to encounter and be confronted with the mystery of God's kingdom.
A couple of verses before this, right, remember last week, Jesus says,
let anyone who has ears listen.
And what Jesus is doing is inviting us in to discover what God is revealing.
Like Kent talked about last week, parables were meant to hit the ears of those who were even actively plugging their own ears.
Let anyone who has ears listen.
It's the same language I use with my kids when they do, when I say something, they don't do it.
Right?
Church, this is us.
So, did you hear what I said?
I'm assuming, children, you did not hear because you did not do.
See, God, I think, works in the same way with us.
The true response to hearing is doing something about it.
True response, true listening requires a response.
Because here's what I've learned.
Jesus' lessons and parables often confront me and my flesh on the direction and initiative that I want to take versus the truth of the kingdom of God.
See, in areas I want to be in control and tell things to God, like, sure, sure we don't try it this way.
The parables confront me and say, boy, play a role.
I told you what the kingdom of God is like.
Are you being honest to that?
Which leads us into the first part of our passage today.
The mustard seed.
Small, insignificant, unstoppable.
If you've spent any time around church, you've probably heard of the parable of the mustard seed.
And I've probably, and again, real people realize, right, I've probably read past this ten times and didn't stop at four verses that I think have huge implications.
My wife, Samantha, actually has a beautiful ring with a tiny mustard seed set inside of it.
And I thought about that as I was kind of preparing the message today.
And that's what the Holy Spirit put in my heart, that this tiny mustard seed, one of the, it's a reminder of this teaching and also the one on faith, right, that we're all familiar with.
But the reminder that even the smallest beginnings in God's hands have unstoppable potential.
And Jesus says here, the kingdom of heaven is like a mustard seed.
So again, to get us all in the same mindset, the what is like a mustard seed?
The kingdom of heaven.
That's important.
Because Jesus isn't just giving us a cute story about seeds and plants.
He's telling us what his kingdom is like.
And I worry for sometimes for those of us that grew up in church, right, I'm preaching to myself here.
That we either have no real working definition of what the kingdom of heaven is.
Or, like Jesus' original audience, we've quietly built up our own expectations about what it should be.
We're unwilling to let the words of Jesus conform that understanding to what he says it is.
Just real quick, before I go any further, I may slip up, so I want to get on stable ground with you guys.
You'll hear me use the phrases kingdom of heaven and kingdom of God somewhat interchangeably.
Matthew, kind of our source text today, tends to say kingdom of heaven out of reverence for God's name because he's speaking to a primarily Jewish audience.
But he's talking about the same beautiful reality.
That the rule and reign of God breaking into the world through Jesus.
And that's where we have to be careful, church.
I'm going to say, I already said I'm going to step up, so I might as well do it.
Yeah.
This is where we have to be careful.
I think we need, need, that's important, we need to build a theology of the kingdom of understanding what God is doing.
We need to do that, right?
You heard me.
Yep, we need, I think we need to do the work of building a kingdom theology.
We need to do the work of building a kingdom theology because we need to understand and see how God operates and works.
And we pray this in the Lord's Prayer.
Your kingdom come.
Your will be done.
I think we have no expectation for what God's kingdom can look like.
We easily become pessimistic and even depressed around the current affairs because we don't know what to do with them.
In light of Jesus.
We can't see kingdom work because we don't know where to look.
Because we have no established framework for it.
But here's the tension.
Tons of tension.
At the same time, you need to do the work of building a kingdom theology.
You also need to hold it so loosely that when Jesus tells us a parable, he can reframe us, not the other way around.
We should do the work of building a kingdom theology because I believe kingdom understanding is our kingdom ethic.
Corey, what do you mean by that?
I mean that the way you and I understand the kingdom of God drives our Christian ethics.
Think about that.
In other words, what we believe about God's rule and reign will shape how we live it out.
If we think God's kingdom is about power, control, and being on top, that's how we're going to live it out.
But if we believe the kingdom is about sacrifice, service, love, and small act of obedience, then that's how we're going to live it out.
Because kingdom understanding is our kingdom ethic.
But Jesus says the kingdom is like a mustard seed.
What does that mean?
Small and slow, hidden and humble, yet it transforms everything from the inside out.
Does that make sense?
My kingdom?
Oh, jiving?
Tracking?
Because if we come to these parables with no thought of what the kingdom of heaven is or how it operates, these parables do little to shape us.
They are just a word count.
They're just reading, right?
They do nothing to shape our understanding of the kingdom.
But on the other hand, if we come to the parables thinking we already know how the kingdom of heaven should work,
we might miss the small, surprising, hidden ways that God actually chooses to move.
Jesus knew this, so he utilizes the tools of parables to get past our defenses
and present the truest information about what the kingdom of heaven is actually like.
N.T. Wright says this.
My wife laughed at me because I quote N.T. Wright all the time.
But Jesus' stories are not just good advice.
They are designed to break open worldviews and reconstruct them around the reality of God's reign.
One of the most surprising pictures Jesus gives is the parable of the mustard seed.
But I want you to remember back to last week what Kent said, don't remember the parables by their names.
Then we get into a very shallow understanding of the parables.
So what do we need to do?
Slow down.
Let's take a closer look.
When we do, I think we'll realize that the teaching of Jesus is something far more radical than you and I usually realize with first claim.
See, most scholars believe Jesus is referring to the black mustard plant,
which was common around the Middle East.
And black mustard seeds are tiny.
They're about one to two millimeters.
And they would have been known by the audience among some of the smallest seeds.
I'm not getting into a literal discussion about if it's the smallest seed.
That's not what Jesus is meaning.
But despite its size, the mustard plant can grow to six to 12 feet tall in just a season.
But I think in our minds, we picture, just like Jesus' words, we picture this tree.
But in reality, the mustard seed is more like a giant, unruly shrub than a neatly planted tree.
And here's the key.
While the mustard plant grew commonly in the wild, no self-respecting farmer would have planted one.
So, because it's invasive, it spreads aggressively by seed and root.
And once planted, it will quickly dominate a small plot of land.
Doesn't sound like something a farmer's going to plant.
See, Jesus isn't giving a lesson in botany.
He's describing the outrageous, even disruptive growth of the kingdom of God.
See, this tiny, unimpressive seed, it will take over the garden.
See, for Jesus to say the kingdom of heaven is like a mustard seed that a man took and sowed in his field would have sounded shocking, counterintuitive, and even disruptive to his audience.
Tell us more, because that's not how we do it.
So that's problem one, right?
No sane farmer listening would have intentionally planted a mustard seed.
Jesus wants us to notice the problems and focus our attention there.
It's almost like Jesus is saying, and I tried to make this, like, modern reader, 21st century Virginian lingo.
I don't make it too hillbilly, so you're welcome.
The kingdom of God is like planting dandelions and crabgrass in your pristine, well-manicured suburban lawns.
Would you do that?
No, you would.
No, I'm not doing that.
Why would anybody do that?
But, I mean, the kids will love to blow them.
It's going to look really cute.
You're going to love it.
So try it.
Or, in my realm, in my line of work, the kingdom of heaven is like kudzu or bamboo.
You can't stop it.
And once it sprouts, it spreads wide.
Once it's rooted, good luck trying to get rid of it.
It's there.
The kingdom of God, Jesus says, is like an invasive plant.
Wild, disruptive, unstoppable.
It will spread beyond our fences, beyond our control, and beyond you and I's expectations.
See, this is what most modern readers miss, and I am among the modern readers.
But the people listening to Jesus would have understood what the mustard seed produces is an intrusive weed that will take over everything.
It's not just that Jesus says, the kingdom's like a weed that farmers don't want.
No, it's worse.
He's saying the kingdom is like an invasive force that overwhelms useful crops, monopolizes the moisture, outgrows its competitors, and steals the sunshine.
Jesus wants his listeners to feel uncomfortable with that.
Because the kingdom of God doesn't grow through respectability or careful human management.
It invades, it disrupts, and it spreads wherever it wants.
The kingdom of heaven isn't a curated garden.
It's a wild, unstoppable force.
Folks, hear me.
The kingdom of heaven is not a safe place.
It's unpredictable.
It cannot be harnessed.
It cannot be domesticated.
It is risky, and it is dangerous.
And I'm stepping on my own toes here.
The kingdom of heaven is unpredictable, unharnessed, risky, dangerous.
Friends, I fear that comfort and privilege have made us complacent.
We've been sold a version of Christianity that says, God wants you to be comfortable.
And I want you to read the Gospels in light of this message, especially after Jesus tells a parable.
Be prepared to give up everything, including your life.
Sell everything you have and give it to the poor.
Take up your cross and follow me.
Folks, in real biblical Christianity, everything is on the table.
No one leaves unchanged.
The kingdom of heaven is like a mustard seed.
And yet, here we are, dividing over elections, shouting at each other online, measuring influence by who sits in the seat of power.
All while the true king says, the kingdom of heaven is like a mustard seed.
Now, some good pastoral guardrails.
Because I think we can get into a mindset.
And this is why we do things in community, right?
While I believe all those things about the kingdom of heaven are true and real,
one thing I am not saying about the kingdom of heaven is it is chaotic.
God, throughout the narrative of Scripture, constantly restrains and conquers the chaos monsters.
The mustard seed is not a chaotic picture.
But instead, one that begs the question of us.
Do we allow the kingdom of heaven to disrupt our lives like a mustard seed?
What if that seed pushed us out of our comfort zones and into neighborhoods we'd rather avoid?
What if it pushed us into radical generosity that makes no worldly sense?
What if instead of managing our faith, this is me, what if instead of managing our faith like a garden, we'd let it uproot us?
What I'm saying, folks, and hear me, the kingdom of heaven is like a mustard seed.
I feel like the ShamWow guy now.
But wait, there's more.
The problem, too, the mustard seed really doesn't grow into a tree, right?
We have this picture and expectation in our mind.
We tend to think of something when Jesus references trees, we think of something majestic, towering, like oak trees here in the valley or giant sequoias or redwoods out in the west coast.
Especially when we tend to think of a picture of the kingdom of heaven.
What picture would God use to describe the kingdom of heaven?
But a mustard seed really doesn't grow into that kind of tree.
Again, it's a big shrub.
It's a messy, sprawling bush that takes over.
So the mustard seed isn't what we expect.
What does Jesus mean by a tree that the birds of the air nest in its branches?
So we beg the question.
Jesus, what's with the birds?
Matthew 13, 32.
It's the smallest of all seeds, but when it's grown, it's taller than the garden plants and becomes a tree so that the birds of the sky will come and nest in its branches.
Again, Jesus is not being literal here.
He's tapping into the prophetic language of the Old Testament for his listeners.
Especially Ezekiel 17 and Daniel 4, which Aaron read for us this morning.
But real quick, Ezekiel 17, God plants a sprig from a cedar and it becomes a giant tree where birds of every kind find shelter.
In Daniel 4, Nebuchadnezzar dreams of a tree so vast that it provides shelter for the beast and nesting places for the birds.
See, in prophetic imagery, what Jesus is doing is he's using the birds to represent the nation, the outsiders, the unexpecting ones that are coming to the kingdom of heaven to find shelter.
Jesus is hinting that the kingdom would grow in such a way that even the wrong type of people, the Gentiles, the sinners, the outsiders, would find a home in its branches.
This is yet another scandalous, radical idea for his original audience.
So what is Jesus doing here?
He's doing what I say Jesus is always doing.
And he's turning our understanding of power upside down.
Instead of mighty cedars representing his royal empire, he compares his kingdom to a scrappy, unstoppable shrub.
God starts small on purpose.
Think about Jesus' life, right?
Born in a backwater town to an unwed mother, no riches, no reputation, no political power.
And yet, from his life, death, resurrection, and ascension grew a movement that changed the world.
You and I are here today because of Jesus.
The first century, or think about the 12 disciples, fishermen, tax collectors, nobodies.
Yet, through them and through their testimony, the church was born.
The first century church scattered, persecuted, hiding in homes, yet they grew.
The church father, Tertullian, wrote,
The blood of the martyrs is the seed of the church.
All because a tiny seed was planted.
And it rose up to overtake and fill the garden.
When studying for this sermon, I came across an invasive tree in South Florida.
The Australian pine.
I don't know if we have any Floridians that are familiar with this.
Once the seed takes root, it's nearly impossible to eradicate.
Its roots spread deep and wide.
You can cut it down.
But unless you dig it up by the roots, it will come back.
It's become a serious problem for city governments in Florida.
And how do you control something so evasive, so persistent, so impossible to eradicate?
And while reading that, I could not help but to think of the Roman government and the temple elites.
They were trying to do this with Jesus and his followers, to cut them down, to uproot the movement,
and bring power and control back to where the world says it should be.
But they couldn't.
The roots ran too deep.
The seeds of the fruit spread too fast.
And the kingdom of heaven was already taken over the garden.
This is what the mustard seed looks like.
Once it takes root, it is unstoppable.
Friends, the kingdom of God is not fragile.
It's not delicate.
It does not depend on worldly power.
Once planted, it will grow.
But what's our job in that?
Our vocation.
We need to live and obey the king radically in service to his kingdom.
So I'll ask you.
Are you overlooking what God is doing because it looks so small?
Is there a seed of God's word planted in you that you think is too tiny to matter?
Friends, I would disciple you.
Don't despise small beginnings.
God does his best work beneath the soil.
And remember, Jesus didn't just tell this story.
He lived.
The ultimate mustard seed moment was the death and resurrection of Jesus himself.
When the seed was planted into the ground, buried, dead, and forgotten by the world.
But from that death sprang up the unstoppable life of the kingdom of God.
Paul picks up the same picture in 1 Corinthians 15 when he talks about resurrection.
What you sow does not come to life unless it dies.
And what you sow is not the body that is to be, but a bare seed.
Jesus' death was not defeat.
It was planted.
And his resurrection was the beginning of the great invasion of the kingdom.
Just like a small seed overtakes the whole garden, the risen Christ is taking over the whole world.
Church, this is how the kingdom of heaven works.
Small beginnings, hidden growth, and unstoppable harvest.
Jesus doesn't just leave us with that mustard seed.
I think even 2,000 years ago, his listeners were probably as stubborn as we are.
So he gives us another parable to drive the picture even deeper into our hearts.
The kingdom of heaven is also like leaven that a woman took and hid in 50 pounds of flour until it was all leaven.
All my girls and their bread-making arrows said, amen.
But there's a tension here, right?
There's a, there's a, want us to spot the problem.
At first glance, this feels like a throwaway line.
And I'm pretty sure I love confessing to things we're all probably guilty of, so that makes it a lot easier.
But we've all read past this verse.
It feels like something Jesus had to do to fill a required word count.
It's short, it's domestic, it's quiet.
Like that time we spent on the first part, I would disciple you not to let simplicity fool you.
But this parable is also packed with punch.
Leaven, yeast, it's active, it's alive.
So when you mix a little bit of it into the dough, you can't see it anymore.
Gone.
But with some time and patience, the effects of that leaven are very evident in the dough.
It is going to rise.
It is going to expand.
It may not be as pretty as you want it to be.
But it's going to rise and it's going to expand and the leaven will work into every corner of the batch.
That's what Jesus is saying the kingdom of heaven is like.
Hidden, small, but powerfully transforming.
Jesus is reinforcing the same theme that started with mustard seed.
That God's kingdom may start in obscurity, but it may not look like much.
But once it gets into the mix, you can't keep it from rising.
You can't stop it from spreading.
Here's the tension.
And all my good church people will notice this tension.
Yeast isn't always a good thing in the Bible.
Actually, I'd say that overwhelmingly, yeast is portrayed as a negative symbol.
Something to be cautious of.
So when you heard that, you were like, what do I do with that?
In the Exodus narrative, God told Israel to remove the leaven from their houses during Passover
because it represented Egypt and the old ways of life.
In just three more chapters of Matthew, if you continue reading,
Jesus will warn his disciples about the leaven of the Pharisees,
about their hypocrisy and their corrupt teaching.
Paul uses the symbol in 1 Corinthians 5 to describe how little sin can infect the whole church.
So what is it Jesus is doing here?
Is he flipping the symbol, using leaven to show the quiet power of the gospel?
Or is it a subtle warning like, be careful what people are putting into the dough?
Here's the beauty and tension.
It might be both.
On one hand, Jesus is saying the kingdom of heaven will rise.
It may be hidden, it may seem small, but its influence is unstoppable.
Like yeast, once the kingdom gets into the hearts of people or into the good soil of society,
it goes to work quietly, powerfully, thoroughly because the kingdom of heaven is alive.
But at the same time, there's a subtle echo here, a nudge to be alert, right?
I think it's positive because Jesus starts at the kingdom of heaven is like.
But I think there's a good reason to be hesitant here and to think through that.
A nudge to be alert.
Leaven is powerful.
And folks, not all leaven is good.
Not everything that spreads in the name of Jesus is actually from Jesus.
I hate to break that truth to you this morning.
But just like the kingdom can spread in hidden ways, so too can false teaching, hypocrisy, and compromise to the powers and principalities.
And a little bit can go a long way.
And church, again, confessing to you guys, I live in this tension.
I live in this tension where I have a robust hope and optimism in the kingdom of God.
But I also understand the warning about bad leaven and how it can also be at work.
But rest assured, I believe that God is at work, even when we can't see it.
Isaiah 55, 11 says,
My word will not return to me empty, but will accomplish what I please and will prosper in what I send it to do.
Good leaven is still at work.
And it's still working today.
Take a drink before I drop the hammer.
You guys may not have me back, but that's okay.
No, I'm just kidding.
But here's what breaks my heart, church.
When we don't have a kingdom theology and all we see is bad leaven.
Man, times sure are bad.
This world's going to hell in a handbasket.
Yes, I will concede there is brokenness.
There is darkness.
There is false teaching, but no part of me is denying those facts.
But if the world is dark, that is no time for the church to shrink back.
It's time for the church to shine brighter, to be prophetic witnesses of our King, Jesus Christ,
to call the powers of this world to account and to echo the same language that Jesus echoed to Pilate.
You have no authority over me at all unless it's been given to you from above.
Jesus is reminding Pilate where power truly resides, not in a Roman consul and not in a White House,
but with the true King and his kingdom.
Church, it's time we start living into our calling as kingdom people.
The early church didn't retreat from the brokenness of this world, nor did they deny it.
They marched forward in the name of Jesus.
Where the church saw sickness, they created hospitals.
Where they saw children with no one to love and care for them, they created orphanages.
Where they saw image bearers of God cold and on the streets, they opened missions.
And even participating with government, where they saw slavery, they appealed to Parliament.
Where you see injustices, are you stepping into those injustices in the name of Jesus?
Because I believe the kingdom of heaven is alive and active because every day I see individuals working for the kingdom because it's alive in them.
Because I believe the risen Christ has overtaken the world through them.
You may feel like your witness is unnoticed.
That is a lie of the enemy.
You may wonder if your prayers and your kindness and your faithfulness are making any real difference in this world.
The conversations you have, the acts of kindness, the quiet obedience, all in the name of Jesus is doing more than you and I could ever see.
It's yeast moving through the dough.
It's transforming hearts.
It's bringing into focus for all that the kingdom of heaven is alive and breaking into this world.
I want us to look at Jesus' own life again.
Grew up in a no-name town.
The disciples said, can anything good come from Nazareth?
He preached to crowds, to hurting individuals, one broken life at a time.
He called false witness and false teaching what it was, but invited them into a better way to live.
He was rejected.
He was crucified.
He was buried in the ground like a seed.
But on the third day, that seed cracked open.
From that, the tree of life began to grow.
From one crucified man to Christianity having a foothold in every major, every continent.
From a manger to a throne, from the silence of the tomb to the roar of resurrection life.
The risen Christ is still king, and he's still in the business of kingdom building.
The seed is still breaking through the ground.
The good yeast is still working its way through the dough.
It's happening in homes, workplaces, classrooms, neighborhoods, prison rooms, hospital rooms,
and places you and I will never see this side of eternity until one day we see it in full.
But here's the challenge.
Jesus said nobody lights a lamp and hides it under a bed.
No, they set it high where they can give light to everyone around them.
So what do we do?
We plant the seeds, we mix in the good yeast, and we shine the light.
We plant the seeds of the kingdom by sharing the good news with a friend,
praying with and for co-workers, inviting the lonely to our table,
choosing integrity when no one is watching,
raising our children to know and love Jesus.
We mix in good yeast into the dough by living quiet lives of obedience to Jesus,
showing up in broken places,
working for the justice, healing, and hope in the small corners where God has placed you and I.
And coincidentally, we combat bad yeast by following the ways set forth by Jesus.
And sometimes it will feel invisible.
It will feel slow.
It will feel like nothing is happening.
But thank God the power isn't in us.
The power is in our risen king.
As Paul says in 1 Corinthians 3, 6,
I planted, Apollos watered, but God gave the growth.
You don't have to see it to believe it.
You don't have to control it to believe it.
And it doesn't have to be flashy to be faithful.
Church, don't hide the hope you carry, the love you can give, and the grace you and I have to offer.
You are not insignificant.
The kingdom of heaven is at work through you.
And I'll leave you with these thoughts from our parable today.
I want you to value the small.
Don't dismiss what seems insignificant.
Your acts of kindness, your faithful prayers, your quiet obedience, they matter.
God does big things with small seeds.
Two, I want you to trust the process.
Spiritual growth, cultural transformation, and healing.
All these things take time.
Trust the seed.
Trust the kingdom.
Trust God's time.
I want you to be patient and faithful.
It's good you don't see it doesn't mean it isn't growing.
I want you to stay faithful in your part.
No matter how small it feels.
Four, I want you to be bold.
The mustard seed is tiny.
Once it's rooted, it is unstoppable.
Don't be afraid to plant kingdom seeds in hard places.
Because the kingdom of heaven is unstoppable.
Five, you should be cautious of bad yeast.
The enemy would love nothing more than for you to rally behind something.
That is anti-Christ.
The enemy would love nothing more than for us, the church, to rally behind something that is anti-Christ while convincing ourselves it's for Jesus.
So, test everything.
Every movement, every message, every impulse you and I have tested against the person, teachings, and life of Jesus.
And don't do that alone.
Do it with community, with believers who are grounded in Scripture and spirit.
Don't waste your time.
I can picture it in my Bible.
Don't waste your time chasing conspiracy boards with yarn and thumbtacks, trying to map out every possible string theory.
No, but instead, live into the real hope that is in Jesus Christ, our Lord.
Let the light of the gospel shine in the shadows.
Let the truth of his kingdom expose every counterfeit.
Jesus warns us of this in Matthew 24, 24, for false messiahs and false prophets will arise and perform great signs and wonders to lead astray, if possible, even the elect.
And last, I want you to be consistent.
Have you ever heard the story of someone who came to faith because of a long-forgotten seed planted years ago by a faithful kingdom worker?
Maybe that seed planter was a Sunday school teacher, a neighbor, a friend, or maybe just somebody that left a Bible on a shelf and you picked it up.
Maybe you're that recipient of the gospel.
A conversation from years ago still echoes in your heart even today.
A word of encouragement, a simple act of kindness, a lifelong friend who never gave up on you and continued to chase you down in the name of Jesus.
Jesus is and has worked through all those things to bring about transformation.
You never know how far the kingdom of God is spreading beneath the surface.
You and I are not the commander of the battlefield.
We are the followers.
I'll close today with Galatians 6, 9.
Let us not get tired of doing the good work, for we will reap at the prosper time if we don't give up.
Let's pray.
Father, in Jesus' name, we thank you for your kingdom.
Hidden yet powerful, small yet unstoppable.
Help me to trust you in the small things.
To be faithful in the sowing of seeds and to believe in our hearts and actions that we proclaim your kingdom come,
your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
We pray all this for your glory and our neighbor's good.
Amen.
We're going to take communion here in just a minute.
If you didn't have a chance to grab it and you'd like to, just a reminder, we practice open communion at Canvas,
which means anyone who claims to have surrendered their life to Jesus is welcome to partake in it.
But there are strong warnings in the Bible that if you have not trusted in Jesus, this is not something for you to participate in.
So it's just something for you to observe.
I said last week after Kent's message that there's a part of me that's really excited about this sermon series,
and there's a part of me that's really anxious.
And I think the parable of the mustard seed and the parable of the yeast, which we don't call them that because we don't use names.
Sorry.
The two parables that we talked about today really communicate why I'm both very excited and anxious.
And that is, I think the American church, in the American church, we have, we've done a really good job of making the kingdom clean and neat and organized to appeal to a consumeristic group of people.
And I think we suffer from that as a church as well.
It's just in the air.
And as we really press into what Jesus says about the kingdom, there's going to be some things that we thought were true about the kingdom that we've embraced that feel good and make us feel warm inside and are comfy and cozy.
And Jesus is going to prophetically call us to lay those things down to follow what is true about his kingdom.
And I believe wholeheartedly that if we're willing to do that, it will lead to our good and our neighbor's good, but it'll be hard and it'll be scary.
So let's just keep coming back.
If you're brave, if you're bold, let's keep coming back and laying down our definition of God's kingdom at his feet and allow him to clarify it through his teachings.
Our parable today was about something seemingly small and insignificant that changed everything around it.
I think that would be a perfect way to describe the communion table.
To those outside the church, it's a humble table, the loaf of bread and a cup of wine or juice looks foolish, looks silly.
And yet throughout 2,000 years of history, it has the power to transform individuals from the inside out.
It's seemingly small and insignificant, but it's the place that can change everything.
The communion table is where those who are bitter find forgiveness.
It's where those who are crippled by shame can receive grace.
It's where the addicted can find freedom.
It's where diverse groups of people from every different cultural background can come together and find unity and surrender and love for Jesus.
It's where the poor are provided for.
It's where the lost are found.
The bread, the cup, the body, the blood can change everything.
So if you're a person of the kingdom, I'd invite you to take this wafer, Christ's body, broken for you.
Christ's blood shed for you.
Would you stand and join with me as we recite the Lord's Prayer on our way out?
Whatever version you have memorized, if you don't have it memorized, just move your mouth and nobody beside you will know or judge you.
This is the prayer God gives us, Jesus gives us.
For kingdom people, our Father in heaven, holy is your name.
Your kingdom come, your will be done on earth as it is in heaven.
Give us this day our daily bread.
Forgive our trespasses as we forgive those who trespass against us.
Lead us not into temptation.
Deliver us from evil.
For yours is the kingdom and the power and the glory forever and ever.
Amen.
Go in peace, church.
May the fourth be with you.
Amen.
Thank you.